I remember the magic spell
From back when a rainbow stretched across the sky
In an instant, every corner of the world
Took on a brilliant hue
The voice of my heart
Always illuminates the path I need to take
It is because I doubt everything
That I know it to be true
Why does my heart still beat?
Why do my lungs still breathe?
Why is my chest burning with passion?
There's a reason for all of that
And, like the starry sky hidden behind the clouds
Like the ticket to a destination I lost somewhere
Like the history of the world from before I was born
You hold the answer just beyond my reach
If nothing else, I know that all too well
If nobody else, I know that all too well
Teach Me How to Play Shogi (Continued)
にゃぁ…
ふわぁ…
（二海堂(にかいどう)晴信(はるのぶ)）さあ では次は—
Next I'll introduce the personalities of each type of cat.
一人一人のニャーたちの性格を
紹介するぞ
Okay!
（川本(かわもと)モモ）はい
（川本(かわもと)ひなた）お願いします
Please do!
Yes!
（二海堂）うむ
Good responses.
いい返事だ
Welcome to Shogi Land
（天使のニャーたち）ニャー
Pawn!
He's a hard worker who moves ahead one space at a time!
一歩ずつ前へ進む
頑張り屋さんニャー
My paw
delivers a punch!
（歩兵のニャー）
まだ一番弱いけど
I may be the weakest piece, but there are scenarios where you can't win without meow, so I'm quite important.
My paw
delivers a punch!
僕がいないと
勝てないシーンもある
大事な駒ニャー
Lance!
He's a earnest fellow who's as straight as an arrow!
どこまでもまっすぐな いちずさん
I'll go straight ahead as far as you like!
I'm kind of
clumsy...
（香車のニャー）
まっすぐ前に どこまでも
I'm kind of
clumsy...
But I can't turn back me-round!
後戻りは できないニャー
Knight!
ピョンと跳んで右 左
He can hop around left and right!
Only I can jump meow-ver the heads of friends and enemies alike!
（桂馬のニャー）
僕だけが 敵 味方の頭を
I hop and then
let loose a
kangaroo punch!
I hop and then
let loose a
kangaroo punch!
I hop and then
let loose a
kangaroo punch!
I hop and then
let loose a
kangaroo punch!
I hop and then
let loose a
kangaroo punch!
I hop and then
let loose a
kangaroo punch!
I hop and then
let loose a
kangaroo punch!
I hop and then
let loose a
kangaroo punch!
I hop and then
let loose a
kangaroo punch!
I hop and then
let loose a
kangaroo punch!
I hop and then
let loose a
kangaroo punch!
I hop and then
let loose a
kangaroo punch!
I hop and then
let loose a
kangaroo punch!
I hop and then
let loose a
kangaroo punch!
I hop and then
let loose a
kangaroo punch!
I hop and then
let loose a
kangaroo punch!
I hop and then
let loose a
kangaroo punch!
I hop and then
let loose a
kangaroo punch!
I hop and then
let loose a
kangaroo punch!
I hop and then
let loose a
kangaroo punch!
I hop and then
let loose a
kangaroo punch!
I hop and then
let loose a
kangaroo punch!
I hop and then
let loose a
kangaroo punch!
I hop and then
let loose a
kangaroo punch!
跳び越えることができるニャー
Silver General!
ちょっと斜に構えたクールさん
A cool guy with a little bit of an attitude!
When it comes to cool attacks, I'm purrfect. I'm good for both offense and defense.
（銀将のニャー）
クールな攻めの主役
But I'm
wide
open
from
the
back
and
sides.
But I'm
wide
open
from
the
back
and
sides.
But I'm
wide
open
from
the
back
and
sides.
But I'm
wide
open
from
the
back
and
sides.
But I'm
wide
open
from
the
back
and
sides.
But I'm
wide
open
from
the
back
and
sides.
But I'm
wide
open
from
the
back
and
sides.
But I'm
wide
open
from
the
back
and
sides.
But I'm
wide
open
from
the
back
and
sides.
But I'm
wide
open
from
the
back
and
sides.
But I'm
wide
open
from
the
back
and
sides.
But I'm
wide
open
from
the
back
and
sides.
But I'm
wide
open
from
the
back
and
sides.
But I'm
wide
open
from
the
back
and
sides.
But I'm
wide
open
from
the
back
and
sides.
But I'm
wide
open
from
the
back
and
sides.
But I'm
wide
open
from
the
back
and
sides.
But I'm
wide
open
from
the
back
and
sides.
But I'm
wide
open
from
the
back
and
sides.
But I'm
wide
open
from
the
back
and
sides.
But I'm
wide
open
from
the
back
and
sides.
But I'm
wide
open
from
the
back
and
sides.
身軽で攻守に
すぐれているニャー
Gold General!
The confident bodyguard who protects the king!
王様を守る心強いボディーガード
I like being near the king!
（金将のニャー）
王様の近くが好き
I'm the
claw-nest
cat
who
has
nothing
to
hide.
I'm the
claw-nest
cat
who
has
nothing
to
hide.
I'm the
claw-nest
cat
who
has
nothing
to
hide.
I'm the
claw-nest
cat
who
has
nothing
to
hide.
I'm the
claw-nest
cat
who
has
nothing
to
hide.
I'm the
claw-nest
cat
who
has
nothing
to
hide.
I'm the
claw-nest
cat
who
has
nothing
to
hide.
I'm the
claw-nest
cat
who
has
nothing
to
hide.
I'm the
claw-nest
cat
who
has
nothing
to
hide.
I'm the
claw-nest
cat
who
has
nothing
to
hide.
I'm the
claw-nest
cat
who
has
nothing
to
hide.
I'm the
claw-nest
cat
who
has
nothing
to
hide.
I'm the
claw-nest
cat
who
has
nothing
to
hide.
I'm the
claw-nest
cat
who
has
nothing
to
hide.
I'm the
claw-nest
cat
who
has
nothing
to
hide.
I'm the
claw-nest
cat
who
has
nothing
to
hide.
I'm the
claw-nest
cat
who
has
nothing
to
hide.
I'm the
claw-nest
cat
who
has
nothing
to
hide.
I'm the
claw-nest
cat
who
has
nothing
to
hide.
I'm the
claw-nest
cat
who
has
nothing
to
hide.
I'm the
claw-nest
cat
who
has
nothing
to
hide.
I'm the
claw-nest
cat
who
has
nothing
to
hide.
I'm the
claw-nest
cat
who
has
nothing
to
hide.
I'm the
claw-nest
cat
who
has
nothing
to
hide.
And I love getting close to and then capturing the enemy king too.
だから敵の王様の近くに
寄って行って
捕らえるのも大好き
Rook!
The strongest warrior! A true hero!
最強の戦士　まさに勇者ニャー
I can fly both horizontally and vertically!
（飛車(ひしゃ)のニャー）縦 横 自在に
どこまでも跳べるニャー
老若男女 全てのニャーに
もてもてニャー
I'm popular with men and women of all ages!
Bishop!
A heavyweight missile who's effective diagonally as far as the eye can see!
はるか斜めに にらみを利かせる
重量級ミサイル
I'm a lonely guy who's always risking his life.
（角行のニャー）
いつも捨て身のロンリーガイ
Just be careful, because when I'm attacking, my defense might be weak.
攻撃に気を取られ
防御に もろいところがあるから
気をつけてあげてね
King!
Without me, there won't even be a game.
（王将(おうしょう)のニャー）
僕がいないと始まらない
So don't leave meow alone!
だから 一人にしないでニャー
If I get captured, the game's over.
僕が捕まったら
このゲームは終わりニャー
Therefore, treat me like royalty!
だから“蝶(ちょう)よ 花よ”と
大事にしてニャー
Only the king can move in every direction? Wow!
（ひなた）
王様だけ全部の方向に行けるの？
すごい！
That's right! After all, he's the king!
（二海堂）そう
だって 王様だからね
Swish
しかも彼
But he's also a great fighter in
his own right when necessary!
Swish
いざとなったら
かなりのファイターでもあるんだ
Swish
イエイ
そっか…
I see. So each piece has its own personality!
駒には いろんな性格があるんだ
そう さらに この将棋ランドの
ニャーのすごいとこは
Yeah. And moreover, the awesome
thing about these Shogi Land Kitties
is that when they advance square by square and finally reach the enemy camp...
一歩一歩進んで
敵の陣地にたどり着いたら
何とー！
J-Just one more step to the enemy's camp...
Enemy
Army
（歩兵のニャー）
あと一歩で敵の陣地ニャー
...they can transform!
（二海堂）変身できるんだー
（と金(きん)のニャー）
やった！ 敵陣に入ったニャ
Yes! I reached the enemy camp!
Meowy! I got promoted!
Pawn
Promoted Pawn
(has the same abilities as a gold general!)
ニャーイ
出世したニャー
Congratulations!
The same as gold! The same as gold!
（天使のニャー１）
おめでとうニャー
（と金のニャー）
金と同じ 金と同じ
Please take this!
（と金のニャー）
金と同じ 金と同じ
（天使のニャー２）
これをどうぞニャー
Amazing!
（ひなた･モモ）すっごーい！
Right?
だろ？
（桐山(きりやま) 零(れい)）くっそ 二海堂め
Damn you, Nikaidou...
Hahahaha
Squeee
しかしこの本 結構分かりやすいな
Hahahaha
Squeee
But this book is pretty easy to understand.
Hahahaha
Squeee
Who's the publisher?
どこから出てるんだ？
Hahahaha
Squeee
出版社名が無い
There's no publisher information. Nor a bar code.
バーコードも
And no price, either.
値段も書いてないし
But it looks pretty fancy...
でも やけに豪華な…
Shogi for Beginners Picture Book
Drawn and Written by Nikaidou Harunobu
うっ！ 何ですって
Shogi for Beginners Picture Book
Drawn and Written by Nikaidou Harunobu
What?!
N-N-N-N-Nikaidou, don't tell me you...
に に に に 二海堂 これまさか…
Yeah, I wrote and drew it.
うん　俺が描いた
気付いてくれたか
Shine
You noticed!
Wow! Really?! That's wonderful!
Wow!
（ひなた）ええっ！
すごい 本当に？ すてき！
I wish I could draw like that!
私も こんなの
描けるようになりたーい
魔法？
Is it magic?
分かりやすく描けてるだろうか
I wonder if my drawings are easy to understand.
It came out wonderfully, Young Master! I'm touched!
（花岡(はなおか)）坊ちゃま
すばらしい出来でございます
感激でございます
Yep. Actually, I've loved to draw ever since I was a kid.
（二海堂）うむ　実は小さい頃から
絵を描くのは大好きでな
I wanted to contribute to the popularization of my hobby.
この趣味を少しでも
普及に役立てられればと思ったのだ
で せっかくだから
大東京印刷さんにお願いして
And so, I even asked the Daitokyo Printing Company to throw it together simply like this,
簡単な感じでまとめていただき
二海堂家の新年パーティーで
親族に配ったんだ
then distributed copies to relatives at
the Nikaidou Family New Year's party.
うぉっほん
（ひなた）すごい すごい
（モモ）キャー
That's incredible!
Th-Th-Th-Th-Th...
Deluxe edition
With gold leaf
UV processing
Cloth back cover
Spin
Endpapers
Endsheets
Flower endbands
Trans TUVC
Embossed
Super Fancy!
Throw it together?
簡単な？
いやー 二人とも
興味を持ってくれてよかった
I'm just glad they were interested.
まあ 細かいルールは
Well, the best thing to do is introduce the detailed rules as they go.
おいおい指しながら伝えていくのが
一番だからな
This being the first day, I'm pleased with our progress.
ま １日目にしては上出来だな
おおむね我々は
よくやったであろう
In general, we did a good job.
Yeah!
Clench
こういう小さな一歩一歩を
積み重ねた上に
This is how you build the future, taking one small step at a time!
未来というものがあるのだから
あの…
Um, the station isn't this way.
駅はこっちじゃないですよ
How far do you intend to accompany me?
どこまでついてらっしゃるので？
How far? All the way to your apartment, of course!
（二海堂）どこって
桐山の家に決まってるであろう
What?
へ？
き 決まって… ませんけど…
O-Of course... not. Not, right?
ませんよね？
ハハハ 大丈夫
It'll be fine.
親友の家に泊まるのに
何の遠慮がいるものか
Why would I shy away from sleeping over at my best friend's place?
Actually, let's try to shy away!
しようよ 遠慮
And I'm not your best friend!
っていうか親友じゃないから
（二海堂）アッハハハハ
ま 案ずるな
Well, don't worry about it.
（零）案ずるよ
っていうか案じてよ
I do worry!
And so should you!
Master Kiriyama, Master Harunobu.
（花岡）桐山様 晴信様
Welcome home.
おかえりなさいませ
うむっ
Thanks.
Sorry we're late.
遅くなってしまって すまなかった
よろしく頼む
And now, if you would...
これは右側のクローゼットの手前に
Put that in front of the closet on the right side.
Oh
no
Here are some late-night snacks,
as well as breakfast for both of you.
（花岡）これはお二人の
お夜食と朝食でございます
Oh
no
I couldn't help being concerned about your apartment's lack of daily necessities, Kiriyama.
（二海堂）いやあ 桐山の家は
生活用品が なかなか
そろえられないのが
気に掛かっていてな
Thinking this would be a good opportunity, I picked something out.
よい機会だと思い
見繕わせていただいたよ
This is an excellent bed that folds up into a couch.
このベッドは折り畳むと
ソファーにもなるすぐれものだ
Feel free to use it as you please!
ぜひ使ってくれたまえ
I realize it came late,
but this is my housewarming gift to you!
遅くなってしまったけれどね
君への引っ越し祝いだよ
Teach Me How to Play Shogi
Cat Shogi Sing-along
Let's learn how to play shogi with cats!
You're as straight as an arrow, but you can only go forward
You can't turn back, and you live an earnest yet clumsy life
That's the lance in shogi!
Next up is the silver general!
You're cool because you're the hero behind the scenes
You're good for offense and defense, but you're wide open from the back and sides
That's the silver general in shogi!
Next up is the rook!
You're a strong warrior and a true hero
You're popular with everyone because you can fly both horizontally and vertically
That's what the rook does in shogi! And now you know how to play shogi!
Image
あ… あんのやろう
Th-That bastard.
It won't fit.
入らないじゃねえかよ
What do I do now, huh?!
どうすんだよっ くそー
（松本(まつもと)一砂(いっさ)）
なーに ため息ついてんだ
What are you sighing about?
（零）あ…
一砂さん スミスさん
Issa and Smith...
Huh? Nikaidou isn't with you today?
（三角(みすみ)龍雪(たつゆき)）あれ？
きょうは二海堂は一緒じゃないの？
Oh, that reminds me. I saw the NHK Cup.
あ そうだ
ＮＨＫ杯 見たぞ
Your match, I mean.
お前の対局
つーか 二海堂の熱い解説！
And Nikaidou's passionate commentary.
Did you take all those impassioned lines and etch them in your heart, Kiriyama?
心にちゃんと刻んだか
桐山きゅーん
あの名セリフの数々を…
Friendship truly is a wonderful thing, isn't it?
やっぱ友情って すばらしいよな
Whoa, just thinking about it again pulls on the old heartstrings.
おっと いけねぇ
Doesn't even have the energy
to deny it anymore
思い出しただけでも
ツンっとくるぜ
Doesn't even have the energy
to deny it anymore
I was at my teacher's birthday party the day it aired,
（三角）放送のあった日
ちょうど うちの師匠の誕生会でさ
but we all watched the recording that night.
夜 みんなで録画したやつ
見てたんだけど…
If you really want to win, then persevere!
本当に勝ちたいなら粘れ！
攻めるだけじゃなく
ちゃんと守れ！
Don't just attack, you have to defend!
Nikaidou...
Huh?
あれ？ 何だろ
What is this?
Water coming out of my eyes?
目から水が…
Oh no. I'm going to cry!
やべっ 俺 泣きそう
Wh-What a good kid!
（男性）い… いい子だ
Whoa, what's this?
（師匠）おっと いかん…
年は取りたくないのう
This is what I hate about getting old.
It makes you all sentimental.
最近どうも涙もろくて…
N-Nikaidou! I can't believe you!
（松本）二海堂 お前ってやつは…
（三角）いやぁ もう
大の大人がそろいもそろって—
I'm telling you, we had a room full of adults bawling like babies.
y
*
E
v
e
r
v
y
b
o
d
y
l
o
a
v
e
s
N
i
k
a
i
d
o
u
みんなもう 涙目になっちゃってさ
I heard that after the broadcast,
Nikaidou had a bout of anemia and couldn't get to his feet.
あとで聞いたんだけど…
撮影のあと 二海堂
貧血起こして
座り込んじまったらしいぜ
What? He did?
え？ 二海堂が？
（三角）
エネルギー使ったんだろうな 相当
He must've used up a lot of energy.
He really tried his hardest.
一生懸命だったもんな
Right? And yet...
なあ なのにな…
なあ… もう！
Right? Yeesh...
なーんか お前のハートに
It's kind of annoying since not
one bit of it reaches your heart.
いまひとつ届いてない感じが
ほんっと悔しいんだよな
Nikaidou has six wins. He's incredibly focused.
二海堂は６勝したぞ
ものすげぇ 集中してる
He'll probably get promoted this season.
多分 今期は昇級する
Right now, his head is probably filled with the thought of facing off against you in C1.
多分 今 頭の中は
Ｃ１で お前と戦うことで
いっぱいだ
頼むよ 桐山
Please, Kiriyama! Don't disappoint Nikaidou!
二海堂をがっかりさせないでくれ
（零）３勝３敗…
Three wins and three losses.
ここで踏みとどまらないと
If I don't hold my ground here,
I'll just slide down until I reach the point of demotion.
ずるずると滑り落ちて
降級点が付く
If you get a demotion, it won't get erased unless you have more wins the following season.
一度付いた降級点は 来期以降
勝ち越さないと消すことはできない
２つたまると
下のクラスへ落ちてしまう
If you get demoted twice, you drop down one class.
マイナスを塗り返すための戦いは
The battle to paint over a loss is even more
exhausting than the battle to move forward.
前に進むための戦いより
消耗が激しい
I witnessed my adoptive father go through that
seesawing struggle under the same roof for years
それは…
父のＢ１からの降級がかかった
長年の一進一退を
after he was downgraded from B1.
ずっと同じ屋根の下で
見つめていて…
体じゅうに 染み込むほど感じた
It permeated my body.
Take better care of your shogi, and yourself!
自分を大切に
自分の将棋を大切にしてくれ
頼む！
I'm begging you!
Where does Nikaidou's energy come from?
（零）二海堂の あのエネルギーは
どこから来るんだろう
体だって
決して丈夫じゃないのに
It's not like his body is particularly strong.
自分を疑ったりしないのだろうか
Is it that he doesn't doubt himself?
That passion, always driving him on tenaciously...
前へ前へと進もうと粘る あの熱
そばにいると胸が苦しくなるんだ
Whenever I'm with him, I feel suffocated.
And I gradually become disgusted with myself.
自分が嫌になりそうで…
（川本(かわもと)あかり）それにしても
本当 よく描けてるわね
He did such a great job drawing it.
It sounds like Hina and Momo both had fun.
（あかり）ヒナもモモも
楽しかったみたい
（シロちゃん）ニャ…
I'll deliver you my paw-punch!
（モモ）肉球パンチ
（シロちゃん）ニャー
（モモ）お見舞いするニャー
（シロちゃん）ギニャー
No, Momo. The kitty doesn't like that!
（ひなた）モモ ダメ！
ニャー 嫌がってるでしょ
They even put copies of the picture book on the fridge so they can remember how each piece moves.
（あかり）
冷蔵庫に絵本のコピー貼って
覚えようとしてるくらいよ
When Grampa saw that...
それを見ておじいちゃんは…
They're lucky.
（川本(かわもと)相米二(そめじ)）いいよなぁ
How often does anybody get the
chance to be tutored by two pros?
プロに二人がかりで
教えてもらえるやつなんざ
そうそういないぜ
こりゃぁ もしかしたら
Maybe they'll end up being really good at shogi.
すっげぇ強くなっちまうかもよ
But I can't let them beat me.
こりゃぁ 負けられねえな
I just wish those two guys would teach me. Sheesh.
つーか 俺が教えてほしいよ
全く 世の中どうなってん
んん…
What's goin' on with today's world?
It seems like he's looking forward to
playing shogi with his granddaughters.
（あかり）だって
孫と将棋ができるの
楽しみにしてるみたい
When I think about it like that, shogi really is marvelous.
そうやって考えると
将棋って不思議ね
It's been around for hundreds of years,
何百年も昔からあって
and even now, as long as you have the board and pieces,
you can enjoy it at home.
盤と駒さえあれば
今でも普通に家で楽しめて…
Moreover, once you learn how to play,
it doesn't matter whether you're an adult or a child.
しかも１回覚えてしまえば
大人も子供も全然関係なく
You can have fun playing earnestly.
みんな真剣に楽しめるなんてね
And for your whole life.
それも一生
What a wonderful game...
不思議なゲームね
うわぁ ニャーちゃん変身した！
The kitty transformed!
Akari's words prompted an image of my father to cross my mind.
（零）あかりさんのその言葉で
よぎったのは
父の面影だった
His body would rock back and forth gently,
with his arms folded and his left hand on his cheek.
小さく前後に体を揺すりながら
左手を頬に当てて腕を組む
It was a natural habit that would appear whenever he was focused.
夢中になると自然に現れる父の癖
I enjoyed watching him when he was like that.
その姿を見るのが好きだった
But I could only see it when I did my very best,
which took studying so much that it made my head spin.
うんと勉強して
頭がきりきりとなるくらい
頑張らないと見れなかったけど
Yet I wanted to see that habit, so I desperately tried my best.
その仕草が見たくて
必死に頑張った
Kind, considerate of the people around him, always smiling...
優しくて…
周りに気ばかりつかって
いつも笑ってた父の…
I saw his true face, stripped of all social niceties.
何も取り繕ってない本当の顔
父さんが今の僕を見たら
何と言うだろう
What would Dad say if he could see me right now?
そうだ
That's right.
How could I have forgotten?
何で…
忘れてたんだろう
Right now,
僕は今…
I'm standing in the world of shogi that he longed for.
父さんが焦がれた棋士の世界に
立っているんじゃないか
How?
何で…
何で忘れていられたんだろう
How could I have forgotten that?
How could I forget something so important?
こんな大事なことを…
Kyouko...
香子さん…
（幸田(こうだ)香子(きょうこ)）んふっ
Image
久しぶりね 零…
Long time no see, Rei.
Distant Thunder (Part 1)
（零）小さい頃 真昼に雷を見た
When I was little, I saw lightning in the middle of the day.
It was a fleeting flash of light that seemed to tumble like liquid silver across the blue sky.
水色の空に
水銀をぽろろと転がしたような
淡いせん光
（雷の音）
（零）僕は…
That one moment captivated my heart.
そのはかなさに心を奪われた
たとえ その輝きが…
Even if that brilliance...
did bring on driving rain afterward.
（零）後に重く激しい雨を
連れてくるのだとしても
You look well.
（香子）元気そうじゃない
Why are you here?
どうして… ここに？
Why?
（香子）どうして？
フフ 変なこと言うわね
What an odd thing to say.
姉が一人暮らしを始めた弟を
心配して様子を見に来るのって
Is it so strange for a big sister to worry for her little brother and check on him after he's begun living alone?
そんな不思議なことかしら
駅まで送ります　もう遅いから
It's late. I'll walk you to the station.
What? You're not going to let me in?
なあに 入れてくれないの？
せっかく来たのに
But I've come so far.
Why not?
何でよ
Why not? It's messy, for one.
何でって 散らかってるし
That's fine. Show me.
いーわよ 見せてよ
There's nothing to show.
何も無いですよ 見ても
（香子）ふん へたな言い訳
バカじゃない？
What a poor excuse. Are you stupid?
If there's nothing to show, it can't be messy, right?
何も無いなら
散らかってもないでしょ
ダメです もう終電が…
Just forget it. The last train is—
（香子）冷えたの 足が！
My feet are cold!
I need to go to the bathroom!
トイレに行きたいの！
Don't make me spell it all out for you, idiot!
もう 全部言わせないでよ バカ!
（香子）ふぅ… やっと落ち着いた
They've finally warmed up.
Hey, how old is this place?
ねー ここ 築何年？
It looks like a dump from the outside, but it's surprisingly clean inside.
外見はボロッちいのに
中は意外にきれいなのね
築26年
It's 26 years old.
But the landlord just had it renovated.
でも大家さんが
ちょうどリフォームしたばかりで
（香子）ふーん
ラッキーだったわね
That was lucky for you.
ねぇ 零
タオルちょうだーい
Hey, Rei, get me a towel.
Thanks.
ありがと
ねぇ 何でこの町にしたの？
So why did you choose this town?
It's not like you have any connections here, right?
あなた この町に
何の縁も無いわよね
前 一度 仕事でこの辺に来て
I came here once for work.
I liked it because of the big, beautiful river.
川が広くてきれいだったから
The river?
（香子）川？
What?
何？
Were you a fan of rivers? I can't remember.
あんた 川とか好きだったっけ？
（香子）ふーん
川ね…
The river, huh?
We lived under the same roof for ten years,
but it's like I barely know anything about you.
10年も同じ家で
顔をつきあわせていても
なぁんにも知らなかったって訳ね
（零）え？
（香子）ねえ 寒いわ この家
Hey, this apartment is cold.
Can't you fix that?
どーにかなんない？
ああ エアコン古いから
あんま効かなくて
The air conditioner is old, so it doesn't work well.
ふうん
Fwoop
（零）ああ 勝手に開けないで
Don't go opening things!
Oh, what a brat.
あ〜ら 生意気
This is a fine feather mattress!
なあに 立派な羽根布団じゃない？
It was a housewarming gift.
（零）それは引っ越し祝いで
もらったんです
You must've just gotten it.
ほんと もらったばっかなのね
It doesn't smell like you yet.
あんたの匂いが まだしない
へぇ すごい眺めね
Wow, that's some view.
Is this really the sixth floor?
これでほんとに６階？
It seems higher.
高く見えるわ
川面が低いから？
Is it because the river is so low?
So this is where you've been living.
そう…
こんな所に住んでたの
一人で探して 一人で決めて
You looked for it by yourself, decided on it yourself...
You really are self-centered, aren't you?
ほんと あんたって勝手よね
Dad was feeling down afterward.
父さん 落ち込んでたわよ
How did you rent it?
どうやって借りたの？ 保証人は？
Who's your guarantor?
Chairman Jinguuji.
神宮寺(じんぐうじ)会長が…
Figures.
ふうん やっぱり
He has a soft spot for you.
あの人 あんたに甘いもんね
Kyouko, the last train—
（零）香子さん 終電が…
（香子）あんたが帰れば
Why don't you go back home...
to that house?
あの家に
Dad would be happier if you did.
その方が父さんも喜ぶわ
Hey.
ねえ…
Lend me a T-shirt. I'm sleepy.
何かシャツ貸してよ
眠くなっちゃった
けんかしたの？ 父さんと
Did you and Dad have a fight?
Nope.
（香子）してない
I mean, I haven't seen him.
っていうか会ってないの
I haven't been home lately.
ここんとこ 私 帰ってないし
Are you still with that guy?
（零）まだ あの人といるの？
Good.
よかった
It didn't leave a scar at least.
傷 残らないで済んで
後藤(ごとう)はまともじゃないから
Gotou isn't a sane guy.
あの人はダメだよ
He's bad for you.
That's none of your business.
あんたには関係ないわ
（零）手を上げられたりしてない？
He doesn't get violent with you?
Get violent? With me?
（香子）手を？
私に？
No way.
まさか
でも もし そうなったとして
But if he did,
do you think I'd just take it quietly?
私がおとなしく殴られてると思う？
I'd stab him...
刺すわよ
in his sleep.
寝てるとこ
もう二度と起きれないくらいにね
And he'd never wake up again.
You'd go that far?
そんなに…
Yes.
I love him.
好きよ
だーい好きよ
I truly love him.
眠れなかったの？
You couldn't sleep?
ダメじゃない
But you have a match that decides your class today, don't you?
きょう対局でしょ 順位戦の
Who's your opponent again?
相手 誰だっけ？
That's right. Matsunaga.
そう そう 松永(まつなが)さん
How old is he?
何歳だっけ？
Sixty-four? Sixty-five? Something like that.
64？ 65？
What a fighter.
よ〜く頑張るわよねぇ
He won't move to the free class even after falling to C1
and keeps desperately sticking it out, I guess you could say.
Ｃ１まで落ちてもフリークラスには
移らないで粘り続け
必死の形相っていうの？
I saw him play against Dad once.
父さんと指してるの
見たことあるわ
しがみつくような将棋
It was like he was holding on for dear life.
It was depressing.
うっとうしかった
He must really love shogi if he didn't quit after all that, you know?
そんなになっても
辞められないなんて
きっと ほんとに
将棋が大好きなのね
Unlike you.
あなたと違って
Oh, that's right.
あー そう そう
I hear if Matsunaga is demoted from C1, he'll finally retire.
松永さん Ｃ1から降級したら
ついに引退するらしいわよ
Isn't that a downer?
気が重いでしょ
It's like you're going over there to strangle an old, senile dog.
長生きして老いた犬の首を
絞めに行くようなものだものね
I understand.
分かるわぁ
誰だってそんな役
買って出たくないもの
Nobody wants to be the one to do the job.
It kind of makes you worry.
なぁんか心配なのよね
I thought that in a situation like this,
maybe you're the type to throw the match.
あなたってこういうとき
わざと負けてあげたり
しちゃうんじゃないかとか—
思っちゃって
Seeing as you're such a nice guy.
ほら あなたって優しいから
As she left, the sun shone through her hair,
illuminating it for a moment.
（零）出て行く彼女の髪が…
日に透けて一瞬 鈍く光った
And that light eventually brought on a pounding rain.
そして…
その光はやがて
激しい雨を連れてくるのだ
Distant Thunder (Part 1)
Like a resplendent meteor shower
Your words enter my ears and catch fire
They come together like a school of fish
And form a warm corner in my once chilly bosom
As I stood in place, not knowing the right way to reach out
Your hand reached out to touch mine
And no matter how many nights may pass
That warmth still lingers and pulses within
Your very presence shines a bright light on every part of my life
Your racing heartbeat resonates with my frozen heart and sets it ablaze
Before long, the fire dies out
Leaving just one smoldering ember
Which remains with me and won't ever go away
Living inside of me in a place closest to my heart
Next Episode Preview
Episode 9
Matsunaga Shouichi.
（零）松永(まつなが)正一(しょういち)　７段
7-dan.
Sixty-five years old.
65歳　福島県出身
From Fukushima Prefecture.
A professional shogi player for forty years.
棋士歴40年
Forty years in this world...
この風景を40年…
I wonder how he feels right now.
今 どんな気持ちなんだろう
Well, crap.
（松永）参ったな… はぁ…
（男性）時間になりました
It's time.
Illustration: Terada Katsuya
（二海堂）３月のライオン
次回も楽しみにな
Don't miss the next episode of
"March comes in like a lion" either!
Please buy a copy of Nikaidou Harunobu's "Shogi for Beginners Picture Book."
二海堂晴信著
「将棋はじめて絵本」
一家に１冊 よろしくな！